Chapter 28 Two days are passed.
It is a summer evening.
The coachman has set me down at a place called Whitcross.
He could take me no farther for the summer I had given,
and I was not possessed of another shilling in the world.
The coach is a mile off by this time.
I am alone.
At this moment, I discovered that I forgot to take my parcel out
of the pocket of the coach, where I had placed it for safety.
There it remains, there it must remain, and now I am absolutely destitute.
Whitcross is no town, nor even a hamlet.
It is but a stone pillar set up where four roads meet, whitewashed, I suppose,
to be more obvious at a distance and in darkness.
Four arms spring from its summit, the nearest town to which these point is,
according to the inscription, distant 10 miles, the farthest above 20.
From the well-known names of these towns, I learn in what county I have lighted,
a North Midland Shire, dusk with Mauland, ridged with mountain.
This I see.
There are great moors behind, and on each hand of me, there
are waves of mountains far beyond that deep valley at my feet.
The population here must be thin, and I see no passengers on these roads.
They stretch out east, west, north, and south, white, broad, lonely.
They are all cut in the moor, and the Heather
grows deep and wild to their very verge.
Yet a chance traveler might pass by, and I wish no eye to see me now.
Strangers would wonder what I am doing, lingering here at the signpost,
evidently objectless and lost.
I might be questioned.
I could give no answer, but what would sound incredible and excite suspicion.
Not a tie holds me to human society at this moment.
Not a charm or hope calls me where my fellow creatures are, none that saw me
would have a kind thought, or a good wish for me.
I have no relative but the universal mother, nature.
I will seek her breast and ask repose.
I struck straight into the heath.
I held onto a hollow I saw deeply following the brown moor side.
I waded knee deep in its dark growth.
I turned with its turnings, and finding a moss-blackened
granite crag in a hidden angle, I sat down under it.
High banks of moor were about me.
The crag protected my head.
The sky was over that.
Some time passed before I felt tranquil even here.
I had a vague dread that wild cattle might be near,
or that some sportsman or poacher might discover me.
If a gust of wind swept the waste, I looked up, fearing it was the rush of a ball.
If a plover whistled, I imagined it a man.
Finding my apprehensions unfounded, however, and calmed
by the deep silence the rain does evening decline.
At nightfall, I took confidence.
As yet, I had not thought.
I had only listened, watched, dreaded.
Now I regained the faculty of reflection.
What was I to do, where to go?
Oh, intolerable questions, when I could do nothing and go nowhere.
When a long way must yet be measured by my weary,
trembling limbs before I could reach human habitation.
When cold charity must be entreated before I
could get a lodging, reluctant sympathy important.
Almost certain repulse incurred before my tail
could be listened to, or one of my wants relieved.
I touched the heath.
It was dry and yet warm, with the heat of the summer day.
I looked at the sky.
It was pure.
A kindly star twinkle just above the chasm ridge.
The dew fell, but with propitious softness, no breeze whispered.
Nature seemed to me benign and good.
I thought she loved me, outcast as I was.
And I, who from man could anticipate only mistrust
rejection, insult, clung to her with filial fondness.
Tonight, at least, I would be her guest as I was her child.
My mother would lodge me without money and without price.
I had one morsel of bread yet.
The remnant of a roll I'd bought in a town we passed
through at noon with a stray penny, my last coin.
I saw ripe bilberies gleaming here and there, like jet beads in the heath.
I gathered a handful and ate them with the bread.
My hunger, sharp before, was if not satisfied, appeased by this hermit's meal.
I said my evening prayers at its conclusion and then chose my couch.
Beside the crag, the heath was very deep.
When I lay down my feet were buried in it.
Rising high on each side, it left only a narrow space for the night air to invade.
I folded my shawl double and spread it over me for a coverlet.
A low mossy swell was my pillow.
Thus lodged I was not, at least at the commencement of the night, cold.
My rest might have been blissful enough, only a sad heart broke it.
It plained of its gaping wounds, its inward bleeding, its riven cords,
it trembled for Mr. Rochester and his doom.
It bemoaned him with bitter pity, it demanded him with ceaseless longing,
and impotent as a bird with both wings broken, it still
quivered its shattered opinions in vain attempts to seek him.
Worn out with this torture of thought, I rose to my knees.
Night was come and her planets were risen, a safe
still night, too serene for the companionship of fear.
We know that God is everywhere, but certainly we feel his presence most
when his works are on the grandest scale spread before us, and it is in the
unclouded night sky, where his worlds wheel their silent course, that we read
clearest, his infinitude, his omnipotence, his omnipresence.
I had risen to my knees to pray for Mr. Rochester.
Looking up, I, with tear-dimmed eyes, saw the mighty Milky Way, remembering what
it was, what countless systems their swept space like a soft trace of light.
I felt the might and strength of God, sure as I of
his efficiency to save what he had made, convinced.
I grew that neither earth should perish nor one of the souls it treasured.
I turned my prayer to Thanksgiving.
The source of life was also the savior of spirits.
Mr. Rochester was safe, he was God's and by God would he be guarded.
I again nestled to the breast of the hill, and air long in sleep for God's sorrow.
But next day, want came to me pale and bare, long after the little birds had left
their nests, long after bees had come in the sweet prime of day, to gather the
heath -honey before the dew was dried, when the long morning shadows were
curtailed, and the sun filled earth and sky.
I got up, and I looked around me.
What a still hot, perfect day.
What a golden desert this spreading more, everywhere sunshine.
I wished I could live in it and on it.
I saw a lizard run over the crag.
I saw a bee busy among the sweet billberries.
I would feign at the moment have become bee or lizard, that
I might have found fitting nutriment, permanent shelter here.
But I was a human being and had a human beings once.
I must not linger where there was nothing to supply them.
I rose.
I looked back at the bed I had left.
Hopeless of the future, I wished but this, that my maker had that night thought good
to require my soul of me while I slept, and that this weary frame absolved by
death from further conflict with fate, had now but to decay
quietly and mingle in peace with the soil of this wilderness.
Life, however, was yet in my possession with all
its requirements and pains and responsibilities.
The burden must be carried.
The want provided for.
The suffering endured.
The responsibility fulfilled.
I set out.
Whit cross regained.
I followed a road which led from the sun, now fervent and high.
By no other circumstance had I will to decide my choice.
I walked a long time.
And when I thought I had nearly done enough, and might conscientiously yield to
the fatigue that almost overpowered me, might relax this forced action.
And, sitting down on a stone I saw near, submit
resistlessly to the apathy that clogged heart and limb.
I heard a bell chime, a church bell.
I turned in the direction of the sound, and there, amongst the romantic hills
whose changes and aspect I had ceased to
note an hour ago, I saw a hamlet and a spire.
All the valley at my right hand was full of pasture fields and corn fields and wood.
And a glittering stream ran zigzag through the varied shades of green, the mellowing
grain, the somber woodland, the clear and sunny Lee.
Recalled by the rumbling of wheels to the road before me, I saw a heavily laden
wagon laboring up the hill, and not far beyond were two cows and their drover.
Human life and human labour were near.
I must struggle on, strive to live and bend to toil like the rest.
About two o'clock PM I entered the village.
At the bottom of its one street there was a little
shop with some cakes of bread in the window.
I coveted a cake of bread.
With that refreshment I could perhaps regain a degree of energy.
Without it, it would be difficult to proceed.
The wish to have some strength and some vigor returned
to me as soon as I was amongst my fellow beings.
I felt it would be degrading to faint with hunger on the cause way of a hamlet.
Had I nothing about me I could offer in exchange for one of these roles?
I considered.
I had a small silk hankerchief tied around my throat.
I had my gloves.
I could hardly tell how men and women in extremities of destitution proceeded.
I did not know whether either of these articles would be accepted.
Probably they would not, but I must try.
I entered the shop.
A woman was there.
Seeing a respectively dressed person, a lady as
she supposed, she came forward with civility.
How could she serve me?
I was seized with shame.
My tongue would not utter the request I had prepared.
I dared not offer her the half-worn gloves, the creased hankerchief.
Besides, I felt it would be absurd.
I only begged permission to sit down a moment as I was tired.
Disappointed in the expectation of a customer, she coolly exceeded to my request.
She pointed to a seat.
I sank into it.
I felt sorely urged to weep.
But conscious how unseasonable such a manifestation would be, I restrained it.
Soon, I asked her, if there were any dressmaker or plain workwoman in the village.
Yes, two or three, quite as many as there was employment for.
I reflected.
I was driven to the point now.
I was brought face to face with necessity.
I stood in the position of one without a resource, without a friend, without a coin.
I must do something.
What?
I must apply somewhere.
Where?
Did she know of any place in the neighborhood where a servant was wanted?
Nay, she couldn't say.
What was the chief trade in this place?
What did most of the people do?
Some were farm laborers, a good deal worked at
Mr. Oliver's needle factory and at the foundry.
Did Mr. Oliver employ women?
Nay, it was men's work.
And what did the women do?
Inault was the answer.
Some does one thing and some another.
Poor folkmen get on as they can.
She seemed to be tired of my questions.
And indeed, what claim had I to importune her?
A neighbor or two came in.
My chair was evidently wanted.
I took leave.
I passed up the street, looking as I went at all
the houses to the right hand and to the left.
But I could discover no pretext, nor see an inducement to enter any.
I rambled around the hamlet, going sometimes to a
little distance and returning again for an hour or more.
Much exhausted and suffering greatly now for want of food.
I turned aside into a lane and sat down under the hedge.
Air many minutes had elapsed.
I was again on my feet, however, and again searching something,
a resource or at least an informant.
A pretty little house stood at the top of the lane, with a garden before it,
exquisitely neat and brilliantly blooming.
I stopped at it.
What business had I to approach the white door or touch the glittering knocker?
In what way could it possibly be the interest
of the inhabitants of that dwelling to serve me?
Yet, I drew near and knocked.
A mild-looking, cleanly-attired young woman opened the door.
In such a voice as might be expected from a hopeless heart and fainting frame,
a voice wretchedly low and faltering, I asked if a servant was wanted here.
No, said she, we do not keep a servant.
Can you tell me where I could get employment of any kind?
I continued.
I am a stranger without acquaintance in this place.
I want some work, no matter what.
But it was not her business to think for me or to seek a place for me.
Besides, in her eyes, how doubtful must have appeared my character, position, tail.
She shook her head.
She was sorry she could give me no information.
And the white door closed, quite gently and civilly, but it shut me out.
If she had held it open a little longer, I believe I should
have begged a piece of bread, for I was now brought low.
I could not bear to return to the sordid village,
where besides no prospect of aid was visible.
I should have longed rather to deviate to a wood I saw not far off, which appeared
in its thick shade to offer inviting shelter.
But I was so sick, so weak, so nored with nature's cravings.
Instinct kept me roaming round the boats where there was a chance of food.
Solitude would be no solitude, rest no rest, while the vulture hunger,
thus sank beak and talons in my side.
I drew near houses, I left them and came back again, and again I wandered away,
always repelled by the consciousness of having no claim
to ask, no right to expect interest in my isolated lot.
Meantime, the afternoon advanced, while I thus wandered about like a lost
and starving dog, in crossing a field I saw the church spire before me.
I hastened towards it.
Near the churchyard, and in the middle of a garden, stood a well built, though small
house, which I had no doubt was the parsinage.
I remembered that strangers who arrive at a place where they have no friends and who
want employment, sometimes apply to the clergyman for introduction and aid.
It is the clergyman's function to help, at least
with advice, those who wished to help themselves.
I seem to have something like a right to seek council here.
Renewing, then, my courage, and gathering my feeble remains of strength I pushed on,
I reached the house and knocked at the kitchen door.
An old woman opened.
I asked, was this the parsinage?
Yes.
Was the clergyman in?
No.
Would he be in soon?
He was gone from home, to a distance?
Not so far.
Happened three mile.
He had been called away by the sudden death of his father.
He was at marsh end now and would very likely stay there a fortnight longer.
Was there any lady of the house?
Nay, there was not but her, and she was housekeeper.
And of her, reader, I could not bear to ask
the relief for one of which I was sinking.
I could not yet beg.
And again, I crawled away.
Once more, I took off my handkerchief.
Once more, I thought of the cakes of bread in the little shop.
Oh, for but a crust.
For but one mouthful to lay the pang of famine.
Instinctively, I turned my face again to the village.
I found the shop again.
And I went in.
And though others were there, besides the woman, I ventured the request.
Would she give me a role for this handkerchief?
She looked at me with evidence suspicion.
Nay, she never sold stuff with that way.
Almost desperate.
I asked for half a cake.
She again refused.
How could she tell where I had got the handkerchief?
She said.
Would she take my gloves?
No.
What could she do with them?
Reader.
It is not pleasant to dwell on these details.
Some say, there is enjoyment in looking back to painful experience past.
But at this day, I can scarcely bear to review the times to which I allude.
The moral degradation, blent with the physical suffering, formed to distressing
a recollection ever to be willingly dwelt on.
I blamed none of those who repulsed me.
I felt it was what was to be expected, and what could not be helped.
An ordinary beggar is frequently an object of
suspicion, a well-dressed beggar inevitably so.
To be sure, what I begged was employment.
But whose business was it to provide me with employment?
Not certainly that of persons who saw me then for the
first time, and who knew nothing about my character.
And as to the woman who would not take my handkerchief in exchange for her bread,
why she was right, if the offer appeared to
her sinister, or the exchange unprofitable.
Let me condense now, I am sick of the subject.
A little before dark, I passed a farmhouse, at the open door of which the
farmer was sitting, eating his supper of bread and cheese.
I stopped and said, will you give me a piece of bread, for I am very hungry.
He cast on me a glance of surprise, but without answering,
he cut a thick slice from his loaf and gave it to me.
I imagine he did not think I was a beggar, but only an
eccentric sort of lady who had taken a fancy to his brown loaf.
As soon as I was out of sight of his house, I sat down and ate it.
I could not hope to get a lodging under a roof,
and sort it in the wood I have before alluded to.
But my night was wretched, my rest broken, the ground was damp, the air cold.
Besides, intruders passed near me more than once,
and I had again and again to change my quarters.
No sense of safety or tranquility befriended me.
Towards morning, it rained, the whole of the following day was wet.
Do not ask me, reader, to give a minute account of that day, as before I sought
work, as before I was repulsed, as before I starved.
But once did food pass my lips, at the door of a cottage I saw a little
girl about to throw a mess of cold porridge into a pig trough.
Will you give me that?
I asked.
She stared at me.
Mother, she exclaimed.
There is a woman wants me to give her these porridge.
Well, lass, replied a voice within.
Give it her if she's a beggar, to pig doesn't want it.
The girl emptied the stiffened mold into my hand, and I devoured it ravenously.
As the wet twilight deepened, I stopped in a solitary
bridal path, which I had been pursuing an hour or more.
My strength is quite failing me, I said, in a soliloquy.
I feel I cannot go much farther.
Shall I be an outcast again this night?
While the rain descends so must I lay my head on the cold, drenched ground.
I fear I cannot do otherwise, for who will receive me?
But it will be very dreadful, with this feeling of hunger, faintness, chill,
and this sense of desolation, this total prostration of hope.
In all likelihood, though, I should die before morning.
And why cannot I reconcile myself to the prospect of death?
Why do I struggle to retain a valueless life?
Because I know, or believe, Mr. Rochester is living.
And then, to die of want and cold is a fate to which nature cannot submit passively.
Oh, Providence, sustain me a little longer, aid direct me.
My glazed eye wandered over the dim and misty landscape.
I saw I had strayed far from the village.
It was quite out of sight.
The very cultivation surrounding it had disappeared.
I had, by crossways and by paths, once more drawn near the tract of Moorland.
And now, only a few fields, almost as wild and unproductive as the heath from which
they were scarcely reclaimed lay between me and the dusky hill.
Well, I would rather die younger than in a street or on a frequented road,
I reflected.
And far better that crows and ravens, if any ravens there be in these regions,
should pick my flesh from my bones than that they should be prisoned in a
workhouse coffin and molder in a pauper's grave.
To the hill then, I turned.
I reached it.
It remained now only to find a hollow where I could
lie down and feel at least hidden, if not secure.
But all the surface of the waste looked level.
It showed no variation but of tint, green, where Russian moss overgrew the
marshes, black, where the dry soil bore only heath.
Dark as it was getting, I could still see these changes, though but as mere
alternations of light and shade, for colour had faded with the daylight.
My eye still roved over the sullen swell and along the more edge, vanishing amidst
the wildest scenery, when at one dim point far in among the marshes and the ridges,
a light sprang up.
That is an igneous fatuous, was my first
thought, and I expected it would soon vanish.
It burnt on, however, quite steadily, neither receding nor advancing.
Is it then a bonfire just kindled, I questioned?
I watched to see whether it would spread but no,
as it did not diminish so it did not enlarge.
It may be a candle in a house, I then conjectured.
But if so, I can never reach it.
It is much too far away, and where it within a yard of me, what would it avail?
I should but knock at the door to have it shut in my face.
And I sank down where I stood and hid my face against the ground.
I lay still a while.
The night wind swept over the hill and over me, and died moaning in the distance.
The rain fell fast, wetting me a fresh to the skin.
Could I but have stiffened to the still frost?
The friendly numbness of death, it might have pelted on.
I should not have felt it.
But my yet living flesh shuddered at its chilling influence.
I rose there long.
The light was yet there, shining dim but constant through the rain.
I tried to walk again.
I dragged my exhausted limbs slowly towards it.
It led me a slant over the hill.
Through a wide bog, which would have been impossible in winter,
and was splashy and shaking even now, in the height of summer.
Here I fell twice.
But as often I rose and rallied my faculties.
This light was my fore-lawn hope.
I must gain it.
Having crossed the marsh, I saw a trace of white over the more.
I approached it.
It was a road or a track.
It led straight up to the light, which now beamed from a sort of knoll
amidst a clump of trees, furs apparently, from what I could distinguish of the
character of their forms and foliage through the gloom.
My star vanished as I drew near.
Some obstacle had intervened between me and it.
I put out my hand to feel the dark mass before me.
I discriminated the rough stones of a low wall above it, something like palisades,
and within a high and prickly hedge.
I grouped on.
Again, a whitish object gleamed before me.
It was a gate, a wicked.
It moved on its hinges as I touched it.
On each side stood a sable bush, holly or you.
Entering the gate and passing the shrubs, the silhouette of a house rose to view
black, low and rather long, but the guiding light shone nowhere.
All was obscurity.
Were the inmates retired to rest?
I feared it must be so.
In seeking the door, I turned an angle.
They are shot out the friendly gleam again, from the lozenged pains of a very
small lattice window within a foot of the ground, made still smaller by the growth
of ivy or some other creeping plant, whose leaves clustered thick over the
portion of the house wall in which it was set.
The aperture was so screened and narrow that
curtain or shutter had been deemed unnecessary.
And when I stooped down and put aside the spray of foliage shooting over it,
I could see all within.
I could see clearly a room with a sanded floor, clean scoured, a dresser of walnut
with pewter plates ranged in rows, reflecting
the redness and radiance of a glowing pit fire.
I could see a clock, a white deal table, some chairs, the candle whose ray had been
my beacon, burnt on the table, and by its light, an elderly woman,
somewhat rough looking, but scrupulously clean
like all about her, was knitting a stocking.
I noticed these objects cursually only.
In them there was nothing extraordinary.
A group of more interest appeared near the hearth, sitting
still amidst the rosy piece and warmth suffusing it.
Two young, graceful women, ladies in every point, sat one in a low rocking chair,
the other on a lower stool.
Both wore deep mourning of crape and bombazine, which
somber garb singularly set off very fair necks and faces.
A large old pointer dog rested its massive head on the knee of one girl.
In the lap of the other was cushioned a black cat.
A strange place was this humble kitchen for such occupants.
Who were they?
They could not be the daughters of the elderly person at the table, for she
looked like a rustic, and they were all delicacy and cultivation.
I had nowhere seen such faces as theirs, and yet, as I
gazed on them, I seemed intimate with every liniment.
I cannot call them handsome.
They were too pale and grave for the word.
As they each bent over a book, they looked thoughtful almost to severity.
A stand between them supported a second candle and two great volumes, to which
they frequently referred, comparing them seemingly with the smaller books they held
in their hands, like people consulting a
dictionary to aid them in the task of translation.
This scene was as silent as if all the figures had
been shadows and the fire lit apartment a picture.
So hushed was it.
I could hear the cinders fall from the grate, the clock tick in its obscure
corner, and I even fancied I could distinguish
the click-click of the woman's knitting needles.
When, therefore, a voice broke the strange
stillness at last, it was audible enough to me.
Listen, Diana, said one of the absorbed students.
France and Old Daniel are together in the night time, and France is telling a dream
from which he has awakened in terror, listen.
And in a low voice, she read something, of which not one word was intelligible to me.
For it was in an unknown tongue, neither French nor
Latin, whether it were Greek or German, I could not tell.
That is strong, she said, when she had finished.
I relish it.
The other girl, who had lifted her head to listen to her sister, repeated while she
gazed at the fire, a line of what had been read.
At a later day, I knew the language and the book.
Therefore, I will hear, quote, the line.
Though when I first heard it, it was only like a stroke on sounding brass to me,
conveying no meaning.
Da trat hevo Ina, anzu sehenvidee stern ennucked.
Good, good, she exclaimed, while her dark and deep eyes sparkled.
There you have a dim and mighty archangel fitly set before you.
The line is worth a hundred pages afustian.
Ich wager dae, geranken, in der Schale minus, zornes
und dae, werke mit dem gervisch -de-minus grims.
I like it, both were again silent.
Is there only country where they talk of that way?
Asked the old woman, looking up from her knitting.
Yes, Hannah, a far larger country than England, where they talk in no other way.
Well, for sure case, I naunt how they can understand to one other.
And if either of you went there, you could tell what they said, I guess.
We could probably tell something of what they said, but not all.
For we are not as clever as you think us, Hannah, we don't speak German and we
cannot read it without a dictionary to help us.
And what good does it do you?
We mean to teach it some time, or at least the elements as they say,
and then we shall get more money than we do now.
Very like, but give our studying, you've done for tonight.
I think we have, at least I'm tired.
Mary, are you?
Mortally, after all, it's tough work, fagging
away at a language with no master but a lexicon.
It is, especially such a language as this crabbed but glorious Deutsche.
I wonder when Sinjin will come home.
Surely he will not be long now, it is just ten,
looking at a little gold what she drew from her girdle.
It rains fast, Hannah.
Will you have the goodness to look at the fire in the parlour?
The woman rose.
She opened a door, through which I dimly saw a passage.
Soon I heard her stir a fire in an inner room.
She presently came back.
Ah, a children, said she.
It fear troubles me to go into a young room now.
It looks so lonesome with the chair empty and set back in a corner.
She wiped her eyes with her apron.
The two girls, grave before, looked sad now.
But he is in a better place, continued Hannah.
We shouldn't wish him here again, and then
nobody need to have acquired a death nor he had.
You say he never mentioned us, inquired one of the ladies.
He hadn't time, Ben.
He was gone in a minute was your father.
He had been a bit ailing like the day before, but not to signify.
And when Mr. Sinjin asked if he would like either
a key to be sent for, he fair laughed at him.
He began again with a bit of a heaviness in his head the next day.
That is, a fortnight sin.
And he went to sleep and never wakened.
He were almost stuck when your brother went into the chamber and found him.
Ah, children, that's the last of the old stock.
For ye and Mr. Sinjin is like of different sort to them, it's gone.
For all your mother-worm is she your way, and a most as book learned.
She were the picture or your Mary.
Diana is more like your father.
I thought them so similar, I could not tell where the old
servant, for such I now concluded her to be, saw the difference.
Both were fair, complexion and slenderly made.
Both possessed faces full of distinction and intelligence.
One to be sure had hair a shade darker than the other,
and there was a difference in their style of wearing it.
Mary's pale brown locks were parted and braided smooth.
Diana's dusky attresses covered her neck with thick curls.
The clock struck ten.
You'll want your supper, I am sure, observed Hannah, and so will Mr.
Sinjin when he comes in.
And she proceeded to prepare the meal.
The ladies rose.
They seemed about to withdraw to the parlor.
Till this moment, I had been so intent on watching them.
Their appearance and conversation had excited in me so keen and interest.
I had half forgotten my own wretched position.
Now it recurred to me.
More desolate, more desperate than ever it seemed from contrast.
And how impossible did it appear to touch the inmates of this house with concern on
my behalf, to make them believe in the truth of my wants and woes, to induce them
to vouch safe arrest for my wanderings, as I
groped out the door and knocked at it hesitatingly.
I felt that last idea to be a mere Kimmerer.
Hannah opened.
What do you want?
She inquired in a voice of surprise, as she
surveyed me by the light of the candle she held.
May I speak to your mistresses, I said.
You had better tell me what you have to say to them.
Where do you come from?
I am a stranger.
What is your business here at this hour?
I want a night's shelter in an outhouse or anywhere, and a morsel of bread to eat.
Distrust, the very feeling I dreaded, appeared in Hannah's face.
I'll give you a piece of bread, she said, after a pause.
But we can't take in a vagrant to lodge.
It isn't likely.
Do let me speak to your mistresses.
No, not I.
What can they do for you?
You should not be roving about now.
It looks very ill.
But where shall I go if you drive me away?
What shall I do?
Oh, I'll warrant you know where to go and what to do.
Mind you don't do wrong, that's all.
Here is a penny.
Now go.
A penny cannot feed me, and I have no strength to go farther.
Don't shut the door.
Oh, don't for God's sake.
I must.
The rain is driving in.
Tell the young ladies, let me see them.
Indeed, I will not.
You are not what you ought to be, or you wouldn't make such a noise.
Move off.
But I must die if I'm turned away.
Not you.
I'm feared you have some ill plans again that bring
you about folks' houses at this time of night.
If you have any followers, housebreakers or such like, anywhere
near, you may tell them we are not by ourselves in the house.
We have a gentleman, and dogs, and guns.
Hear the honest but inflexible servant clapped the door to and bolted it within.
This was the climax, a pang of exquisite suffering, a throw of true despair,
rent and heaved my heart.
Worn out indeed I was, not another step could I stir.
I sank on the wet doorstep, I groaned, I rung my hands, I wept in utter anguish.
Oh, this specter of death.
Oh, this last hour, approaching in such horror.
Alas, this isolation, this banishment from my kind.
Not only the anchor of hope, but the footing of fortitude was gone,
at least for a moment.
But the last I soon endeavoured to regain.
I can but die, I said, and I believe in God.
Let me try to wait his will in silence.
These words, I not only thought, but uttered, and thrusting back all my
misery into my heart, I made an effort to compel it to remain there, dumb and still.
All men must die, said a voice quite close at hand, but all
are not condemned to meet a lingering and premature doom.
Such as yours would be if you perished here of want.
Who or what speaks, I asked, terrified at the unexpected sound, and incapable now of
deriving from any occurrence a hope of aid.
A form was near, what form, the pitch-dark knight and
my infeebled vision prevented me from distinguishing.
With a loud, long knock, the newcomer appealed to the door.
Is it you, Mr. Shingin?
cried Hannah, yes, yes, open quickly.
Well, how wet and cold you must be, such a wild night as it is.
Come in, your sisters are quite uneasy about
you and I believe there are bad folks about.
There has been a beggar woman.
I declare she has not gone yet.
Lay down there.
Get up for shame.
Move off, I say.
Hush, Hannah.
I have a word to say to the woman.
You have done your duty in excluding.
Now let me do mine in admitting her.
I was near and listened to both you and her.
I think this is a peculiar case.
I must at least examine into it.
Young woman, rise and pass before me into the house.
With difficulty, I obeyed him.
Presently, I stood within that clean, bright kitchen on the very hearth,
trembling, sickening.
Conscious of an aspect in the last degree, ghastly wild and weather-beaten.
The two ladies, their brother, Mr. Sinjin, the old servant, were all gazing at me.
Sinjin, who is it?
I heard one ask.
I cannot tell.
I found her at the door was the reply.
She does look white, said Hannah, as white as clay or death was responded.
She will fall, let her sit, and indeed my
head swam, I dropped but a chair received me.
I still possessed my senses, though just now I could not speak.
Perhaps a little water would restore her.
Hannah, fetch some.
But she is worn to nothing.
How very thin and how very bloodless.
A mere specter.
Is she ill or only famished?
Famished, I think.
Hannah, is that milk?
Give it me in a piece of bread.
Diana, I knew her by the long curls which I saw drooping between me and the fire as
she bent over me, broke some bread, dipped it in milk and put it to my lips.
Her face was near mine.
I saw there was pity in it, and I felt sympathy in her hurried breathing.
In her simple words too, the same balm like emotion spoke.
Try to eat.
Yes, try, repeated Mary gently.
A Mary's hand removed my sodden bonnet and lifted my head.
I tasted what they offered me, feebly at first, eagerly soon.
Not too much at first, restrain her, said the brother.
She has had enough, and he withdrew the cup of milk and the plate of bread.
A little more syngin, look at the airvidity in her eyes.
No more at present, sister.
Try if she can speak now, ask her her name.
I felt I could speak, and I answered, my name is Jane Elliott.
Anxious as ever to avoid discovery, I had before resolved to assume an alias.
And where do you live?
Where are your friends?
I was silent.
Can we send for anyone you know?
I shook my head.
What account can you give of yourself?
Somehow, now that I had once crossed the threshold of this house, and once was
brought face-to-face with its owners, I felt no longer outcast, vagrant,
and disowned by the wide world.
I dared to put off the mendicant, to resume my natural manner and character.
I began once more to know myself, and when Mr. Syngin demanded an account,
which at present I was far too weak to render, I said after a brief pause.
Sir, I can give you no details tonight.
But what then said he, do you expect me to do for you?
Nothing, I replied.
My strength suffice for but short answers.
Diana took the word.
Do you mean, she asked, that we have now given you what aid you require,
and that we may dismiss you to the more and the rainy night?
I looked at her.
She had, I thought, a remarkable countenance, instinct both with power and goodness.
I took sudden courage.
Answering her compassionate gaze with a smile, I said, I will trust you.
If I were a masterless and stray dog, I know that
you would not turn me from your heart tonight.
As it is, I really have no fear.
Do with me and for me as you like.
But excuse me from much discourse.
My breath is short.
I feel a spasm when I speak.
All three surveyed me and all three were silent.
Hannah said Mr. Sinjin at last.
Let her sit there at present and ask her no questions.
In ten minutes more, give her the remainder of that milk and bread.
Mary and Diana, let us go into the parlour and talk the matter over.
They withdrew.
Very soon, one of the ladies returned.
I could not tell which.
A kind of pleasant stupor was stealing over me as I sat by the genial fire.
In an undertone, she gave some directions to Hannah.
Air long, with the servants aid, I contrived to mount a staircase.
My dripping clothes were removed.
Soon, a warm dry bed received me.
I thanked God, experienced amidst unutterable
exhaustion, a glow of grateful joy, and slept.